<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle wrytten by Iohn Scory the late bishope of Chichester vnto all the faythfull that be in pryson in Englande, or in any other troble for the defence of Goddes truthe wherin he dothe as well by the promises of mercy as also by thensamples of diuerse holy martyres, comfort, encorrage &amp; strengt[h]e them paciently for Christes sake to suffer the manifolde cruell and moste tyra[n]nous persecutio[n]s of ye Antichristian tormentours: exhorting them to contynue in faythfull prayers, innocency of lyfe, pacience, and hope, that God maye the rather deliuer them, restore againe the light of his gospell to Englande, and confounde all the proude, beastly, &amp; deuelishe enterprises of Antichristes garde, that doo imagine nothing els but ye subuersion of the gospell of Christ, and contynually thruste for the bloud of all true Christians.</title>
            <author>Scory, John, d. 1585.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101221</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837038</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837038</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1342</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11613)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 975:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle wrytten by Iohn Scory the late bishope of Chichester vnto all the faythfull that be in pryson in Englande, or in any other troble for the defence of Goddes truthe wherin he dothe as well by the promises of mercy as also by thensamples of diuerse holy martyres, comfort, encorrage &amp; strengt[h]e them paciently for Christes sake to suffer the manifolde cruell and moste tyra[n]nous persecutio[n]s of ye Antichristian tormentours: exhorting them to contynue in faythfull prayers, innocency of lyfe, pacience, and hope, that God maye the rather deliuer them, restore againe the light of his gospell to Englande, and confounde all the proude, beastly, &amp; deuelishe enterprises of Antichristes garde, that doo imagine nothing els but ye subuersion of the gospell of Christ, and contynually thruste for the bloud of all true Christians.</title>
                  <author>Scory, John, d. 1585.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>E. van der Erve,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Emden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1555]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC; date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Copies vary: The Folger Copy title page has the verso blank and is conjugate; the University of Durham copy title page with verso blank is from the same type-setting but is pasted on a stub, the verso of which shows the remains of a woodcut--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:1342:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1342:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN EPISTLE</hi> wrytten by John Scory the late bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope of Chicheſter vnto all the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that be in pryſon in Englande, or in any other troble for the defence of Goddes truthe: wherin he dothe as well by the promiſes of mercy as alſo by thenſamples of diuerſe holy mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres, comfort, encorrage &amp; ſtrenghte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them paciently for Chriſtes ſake to ſuffer the manifolde cruell and moſte tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Antichriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian tormentours: exhorting them to contynue in faythfull prayers, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of lyfe, pacience, and hope, that God maye the rather deliuer them, reſtore againe the light of his goſpell to Englande, and confounde all the proude, beaſtly, &amp; deueliſhe enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Antichriſtes garde, that doo imagine nothing els but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of the goſpell of Chriſt, and contynually thruſte for the bloud of all true Chriſtians.</p>
            <q>
               <p>In the world ye ſhall haue tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but be of good cheare, I haue ouercum the worlde,</p> 
               <bibl>Iohn. 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Anno. 1555.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1342:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1342:2"/>
            <head>Vnto the faythfull, and moſt vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſouldyours of the great captaine, the Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, that be in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Englande, or any other where in banyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and trouble, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Goddes worde, Iohn Scory willyngly a baniſhed man for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me worde, wiſheth from God our father, the grace, comforte, and ſtrength of his holy Gooſt thorowe our only me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>VVho wyll not (deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt) cal the ſtate of our tyme moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and moſt wicked, yf a man ſhould ſpeake after the maner of men? And who wyl not ſay, that we ſhould not take it in good parte, foraſmuche as a man may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde all godly men (as mooſt meke lambes) to be ſlayne of theyr owne ſheperdes: the litle flocke of our Lorde Chriſt (as fatherles childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to be ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and robbed of theyr owne tutors: And laſt of al the very ſonnes of God to be murthered of theyr owne ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall fathers, as they wolde be called?
<pb facs="tcp:1342:3"/>Who is ſo blynde or ſo foolyſhe, that doth not euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly beholde that ſworde ſprinkeled wyth the bloud of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whyche ought only to be drawen out agaynſt the wycked?<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1. Pet. 2.</note> What is he that viſiting the priſons, goyng to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeates of the vngodly, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng the fury and woodnes of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, beholdyng the gallowes, loking vpon the fyres, whoſe flammes goeth vp to heauen: To be ſhort, who (I ſay) rekenyng the nombre of ſoules of ſuche, as are ſo many diuerſe wayes murdered for the worde of God, dothe not abhorre thys cruel worlde? Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles yf a man wyl conſyder the mater dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, he ſhall perceaue that goddes churche was neuer in any age more happye and more bleſſed, then ſhe is now. For although in theſe our dayes the falſe prophetes, the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of that great An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt the man of ſynne,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> and chylde of perdicion, beyng confederate and conſpyred together wyth the Kynges and Prynces of the earth, haue wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged moſt bloudy battayll agaynſt the churche of Chriſt: yet neuertheles tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the goodnes of our God, ſhe hath moſt valeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t champions, which hath
<pb facs="tcp:1342:3"/>in ſuche wyſe defended her, that they fyghtyng vntyll theyr harte bloude was ſhed out, and theyr bodyes bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to aſhes, haue moſte valeauntly throwen downe, confounded, and put to theyr wyttes endes the ſubtyll and moſt deadly enemyes of God, of hys ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, and of hys catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche and congregacion. O moſt bappye tyme wherin pouertie, nede, pynyng in priſon, fetters, chay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſtockes, rebukes, reuilinges, the dennes and caues of the wyldernes, baniſhementes, gallowes, fyres, and the crueltye of tyrauntes, are agayne reſtored to the churche.</p>
            <p>O moſt happy Ferrar more ſtrong than yron, the late Biſhop and true paſtour of S. Dauids in Wales. O moſt diligent and paynful Hoper, the vigilant watche man, and true biſhop latcly of Glocetour. O moſt hardy &amp; conſtaunt Rogers, Taylour, &amp; Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Tardemaker, Bradforde, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Hichye, anh Cauſon, wyth many more both olde and yong, men &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, maried, wedowes and mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (whoſe names and remembraunce as they are eternal wyth God,<note place="margin">Sap. 3.</note> ſo ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght they not to be forgotten of you)
<pb facs="tcp:1342:4"/>whych in your lyfe tyme called all Englande, and namely London to repentaunce, and faythe in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, and in your deathe gaue them an enſample,<note place="margin">Mat. 10. and. 24.</note> to endure in the ſame to the ende, yf they wyl be ſaued.</p>
            <p>O moſt worthye and bleſſed mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, whych haue by your pacient ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feringes, confounded the malyce of Chriſtes aduerſaries, whych by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of your bloud haue ſealed, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyed, and confirmed, the true catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like doctrine of Chriſtes moſte holy goſpel, in the conſciences of goddes electe and choſen people: whych by the contempt of thys vayne lyfe, haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that ye ſought a better lyfe that periſheth not,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> which is immortal and vndefyled, kept for you in heauen: whych thorowe your moſte willyng and conſtaunt deathe, haue glorifyed your alone and onely ſaueour, and ſtrenghtned hys feble afflicted church and congregacion. You knewe and were certeynly perſuaded (as now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth) that it had ben a moſt vile chaunge for you, to haue redemed the ſhorte vſe of thys myſerable lyfe, with the loſſe of that ioyfull and eternall lyfe. You remembred wel thys ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng
<pb facs="tcp:1342:4"/>of your mayſter Chriſt.<note place="margin">Mat. 10. and. 16. Ioan. 12.</note> He that loueth hys lyfe, ſhal deſtroye it. And he that hateth his lyfe in this worlde, ſhal kepe it vnto lyfe eternal. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, what ſhall it procyt a man, though he ſhould winne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole world, yf he loſe hys owne ſoule? You reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not a lytle to remember, that by your pacient ſufferyng, you ſhould be added and put vnto the nombre and felowſhip of the moſt holy prophetes, Apoſtles, and martyres of Chriſte: Wherof ſome were racked,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> and word not be delyuered, that they myght re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue a better reſurreccion: other ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of mockinges and ſcorginges, moreouer of bandes and priſonment: were ſtoned, were ſawen in ſounder, were te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted, were ſlayne wyth ſwed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, walked vp and downe in ſhepes ſkynnes, in gotes ſkynnes, in nede, in tribulacion, and vexacion, whome the worlde was not worthye to haue. O moſt valeaunt (I ſaye) noble &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed martyres of our age, whych were not murdered, as in old tyme, of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours or kynges that profeſſed ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt hatered agaynſt Chriſt and his churche, but of ſuche as glorie of the tytles and names of the very paſtore,
<pb facs="tcp:1342:5"/>and wolde be counted the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, and fathers of the church, and the faythe of Chriſt. Wherfore be not diſmayed dere brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at thys ſodaine and feruent heate, whych is nowe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g you to trie you, as though ſome ſtraunge thyng had happened vnto you:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> but rather reioyſe, yea I ſaye, a thouſande tymes reioyſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye ſhall not be defended by any earthy power, but by the ſtrong ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the moſt myghtye and mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, and by the moſt myghtye worde of Ieſu Chriſte, whyche was ſharper then any two edged ſworde.<note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note> For what earthy authoritie, what po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, what kynde of armour, what ar tillarye is able to ſuppreſſe ſo great rage and fury, of theſe moſt cruel and mercyleſſe, that woulde yet be called paſtours and fathers of the churche, and defendours of the faythe. Reioyſe I ſay, therfore, for euen as ye be now made lyke vnto the ymage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God in ſuffryng,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.2. Tim. 2.</note> and be partakers wyth hym in dyeng: euen ſo ſhall ye moſte certaynly be partakers of hys lyfe, and raigne wyth hym hereafter in hys celeſtial kyngdome. And do not thynke pour ſelues better than
<pb facs="tcp:1342:5"/>your brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bleſſed martyrs that lately haue ſuffred for the teſtimony of the Lorde Ieſu among you, &amp; your forefathers the holy Prophetes and Apoſtles, but ſaye with them: We are troubled on euery ſyde,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> yet ar we not wythout ſhifte, we are in pouertie, but not vtterly wythout ſomwhat: We are perſecuted, but are not forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, we are caſt downe, neuertheles we are not confounded: And we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes beare about in our bodyes,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> the dyeng of the Lorde Ieſu: We are kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all the daye long, and are counted as ſhepe appoynted to be ſlayne: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythſtandyng in all theſe thynges, we myghtely ouercome, thorowe his helpe that loued vs. Therfore be not afrayed of your aduerſaries, whyche are vnto them ſelues a cauſe of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> but vnto you a cauſe of ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For bothe it hathe ben tolde you afore hande, and alſo it is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you now of God thorowe Chriſt, that you ſhoulde and muſt paſſe thorowe hungre, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, colde, fetters, ſtripes, ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, darke dongeons, ſwordes, gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and fires, and that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furious rage of moſt rauening wolfes ſhould violently aſſaile you. For likewiſe as
<pb facs="tcp:1342:6"/>the churche of our God (as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may eaſely perceyue ſins the fyrſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the ſame) dyd neyther ſpring vp, nor was ſtably ſhed by ryches, by pleaſures, by ydelnes, by eatyng and drynkyng, by the power of kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, by aboundaunce and erceſſe of earthy thinges, by glorious ſtiles, tytles, and woridly pompe, but by the bloud ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng and ſufferyng of the ſayntes:</p>
            <p>Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo in the laſt dayes of thys blynd and bloudy worlde, the moſt glorious ſpouſe of our ſaueour &amp; Lorde Chriſt (which by Antichriſt was almoſt quit baniſhed, and rooted vp) can not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne planted, watered, and eſtably<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but by many ſondry, ſtraunge &amp; truel perſecucions &amp; effuſion of much innocent bloude: whych neuertheles the Lorde wyl as certeynly requyre (&amp; that ſhortly,<note place="margin">Bloudy handes.</note> of the mercyles tyraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of thys worlde, as he requyred the bloud of Abell of the vnnaturall bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and cruel murtherer Tam, and as he required the bloud of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes of that moſte godles &amp; vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cytie Ieruſalem.<note place="margin">Gen. 4. Mat. 23.</note> Be therfore pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient deare brethren a whyle:<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> For within a very lytle whyle, he that ſhal come wyl come,<note place="margin">Iaco. 5.</note> and wyl not tary.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1342:6"/>
            <p> Beholde the huſbande man wayteth for the precious frute of the earthe, and hathe long pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therupon, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl he receyue the early &amp; latter raine. Be ye alſo therfore pacient and ſatle your hartes, for the commyng of the Lorde draweth nye.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> For as many as wyl lyue godlye in Chriſt Ieſu, muſt nedes nowe ſuffre perſecucion. Thys is that waye, thys is that pathe that leadeth vnto lyfe. In thys muſt ye walke, yea rather ye muſte runne in thys: whych we truſt ye wyl do, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as the Lorde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dwelleth wyth you vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worldes ende,<note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> wil not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre you to be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted aboue your ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gth.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> He hathe promiſed to geue you a mouthe and wiſdome,<note place="margin">Luc. 21.</note> where agaynſt all your aduerſaries ſhall not be able to ſpeake, nor reſiſte, (whych promiſe as many of you doo knowe, the Lord dyd moſt truly kepe wyth thaforena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med gloryouſe martyrs, that did late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffer among you) he hathe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that not one heare of your heades ſhall periſhe. Ar not two ſparowes (ſaieth the truthe that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not lye) ſold for a farthing, and one of them ſhall not falle on the grounde wythoute your father? feare ye not therfor (ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:1342:7"/>he) ye at of more valure then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſparowes. All ye therfor that haue pleaſure in ryghtfulnes,<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.</note> and haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of your god writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in your har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, feare not the curſe of men, nor be afrayed of theyr blaſphemyes and reuilynges (ſaythe your lord God) for wormes and mothes ſhall eate them vp like clothe and wolle: neuertheles my ryghtfulnes (ſaythe the lord) and my ſauyng healthe ſhall endure for euer. And the ſaueor of men ſaythe, that he came downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen,<note place="margin">Ioan. 6.</note> not to doo hys owne wyll, but the wyll of hym that ſent hym. And that thys is the fathers wyll that ſent hym, that he ſhuld loſe no thing of all whych he hathe geuen hym, but ſhuld rayſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp agayne at the laſt daye. Therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort your ſelues (beloued bretherne) wyth theſe and ſuche like wordes of the truthe.</p>
            <p>And yf they ſhal purſue you, that you ſhal be compelled to forſake your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue countre, wyth other of your pore bretheren and countremen, &amp; to leue your labors and lyuinges vnto mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyles ſtraungers, and blody papiſtes: Remember that the holl earthe is the lordes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.</note> and all that is in it. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:1342:7"/>alſo howe that holy Dauſo was compelled thorowe the tyranny of Saul,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 28.</note> not only to forſake hys owne natiue countre, but alſo to fle &amp; ſaue himſelfe among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathen idolaters.<note place="margin">Mat. 2.</note> Forget not the moſt innocent babe Chriſt, wyth the moſt pure virgine hys mother, and good father Ioſeph, whych were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled thorowe Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ambycious tyranny to fle in to Egipt. Remember alſo that the ſame God that helped Dauid, and the babe Chriſt in all daungers, and brought them home agayne in to their owne countre, is yet aliue, &amp; as hable bothe to ſaue you now, and alſo to throwe downe your ennemyes, as euer he was. Therfor if ye ſhall be compelled to fle from your natiue countre, ſaye as Danid ſayde, when he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to fle from hys owne citye Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thorowe the rebellyon of hys owne trayterous ſonne Abſalon:<note place="margin">2. Reg. 15.</note> Yf I ſhal finde fauour in the eyes of the Lord, he will bryng me home againe in to myne owne countre: but if the Lord thus ſaye, I haue no luſte vnto thee, behold here am I, let him doo wyth me what ſemeth good in hys eyes, yf they ſhall put you in to priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:1342:8"/>be myndefull of Ieremy, Paule, and Sylas,<note place="margin">Ier. 28.</note> wherof the one was let downe in to a doungeon,<note place="margin">Act. 16.</note> wheare as was no water, but myre: wherin the prophet of God ſtoke faſt: The other two wer thruſt in to an inner pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and theyr fete made faſt in the ſtockes. Yf they wil robbe &amp; ſpoile you of your goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> Remember y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> naked ye came oute of your mothers wombe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tim. 6.</note> and naked you ſhall depart hence: Remember the faithful bretherne of the hebrues,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> whych toke in good worthe the ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of theyr goodes, and that wyth gladnes, knowyng in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that they had in heauen a better and an induring ſubſtaunce. Yf they ſhal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theyr common maner reuile you, &amp; call you knaues, theues, traitours, ſedicious, ſciſmatikes, heretikes, and falſely ſpeake al maner of euel ſayen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges agaynſt you for your mayſter Chriſtes ſake,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reioyſe and be glad, for your rewarde is great in heauen. For euen ſo haue theyr forfathers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiled the holy prophetes, Chriſt, &amp; hys apoſtles. And remembre that ther is no diſciple aboue hys maiſter, nor no ſeruaunt aboue hys lorde.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> Yf you ſhallbe betrayed of your fathers,
<pb facs="tcp:1342:8"/>mothers, brothers, ſuffers, ſonnes, doughters, &amp; of your owne houſhold, familiars and kynſfolke: remember that our ſaueour tolde you,<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> bothe that theſe vnnaturall treaſons ſhould be committed,<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> and alſo that he hym ſelf was betrayed and ſolde of hys owne familiar Apoſtle. yf they ſhall ſawe you in ſounder, thynke on the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Eſay, whych by (the teſtimonie of Eccleſiaſticall writers) ſuffred the ſame deathe. yf they wyl throwe you in to the bottome of the waters and drowne you,<note place="margin">Ion. 1.2.</note> forget not the hiſtory of Ionas. yf they wyll caſte you to the Lyons, or other cruell beaſtes to be deuoured of them:<note place="margin">Dani. 6.</note> Conſyder that the holy prophete Daniel was ſo hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before you. yf they wyl ſtone you to deathe, you ſhalbe in that ſuffering,<note place="margin">Act. 7.</note> companions wyth the fyrſt martyr Stephen. yf they wyll ſtryke of your heades wyth the ſworde,<note place="margin">Mat. 14.</note> remember that Iohn the Baptiſte hade the ſame ende. yf they wyll vniuſtly laye ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion or treaſon vnto your charge, &amp; ſo hang you vp on the gallowes, loke vp to your head &amp; maiſter Chriſt, whych was in like maner vniuſtly accuſed of the ſame crymes,<note place="margin">Luc<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> &amp; ſo han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:1342:9"/>vpon the tre among malefactors and theues. yf they will cut oute your tonges and pulle your ſkynnes ouer your eares, you haue a moſt noble enſample to beholde, the moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mother and hyr vii. ſonnes, in the .ii. boke of the Machabeis: And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt wicked enterpriſes of thys tyme,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mach. 7</note> in reſtoring idolatrous and falſe religion, and perſecuting the true chriſtians, is muche like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tyrannous time of Antiochus: Reade diligently I praye you among other thynges, the foure fyrſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the fyrſt boke of the Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees, and the .vi. and .vii. chapter of the ſeconde boke. Wherby you maye be both comforted in your afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and alſo be the leſſe offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, that now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people by heapes, ſome for flatery, ſome for feare, and ſome for filthy lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, forſake the lawe of the Lorde, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte muche euel in the lande, chaſe out the ſecrete chriſtians, whych had hid themſelues in corners and preuy places,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mach. 1.</note> &amp; ioyne themſelues vnto the Papiſtes, runnyng an horyng after theyr moſt falſe, hypocritical and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable worſhippinges, as they were wode. For euen to dyd they in
<pb facs="tcp:1342:9"/>the tyme of the cruel tyraunte Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus, as you maye perceiue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte and ſecond chapters, of the fyrſt boke of the Machabees. And therfore if you ſhall perceiue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any for feare of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſhall ſhrinke and recante the open truthe of Chriſtes holy doctrine (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the curſed papiſtes deſire chieflye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo they maye gratefie theyr father y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Deuel,<note place="margin">Ioan. 8.</note> in murderyng bothe ſoules &amp; bodies) remember that Chriſt hathe bothe tolde you aforehand of ſuche ſhrinkers in the parable of the ſower,<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> by the ſede that fell vpon the rocke: And alſo that al hys apoſtles ſhronke from him in hys moſt trouble:<note place="margin">math. 26.</note> and of them, one denied and abiured hym, as the Papiſtes now compelle men to abiure that truthe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt then the noone daye: reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber alſo,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.</note> that when Paule was firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented before Nero in iudgement at Rome, all the brethren forſoke him: for whome he prayeth vnto God, that he will not laye that ſhrinkyng and backeſlydyng vnto theyr charges.</p>
            <p>Therfore yf ſuche thynges haue or ſhal happen, be nothyng diſcouraged (dearely beloued) to continue your fyght agaynſt Antichriſt,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.</note> (as ye haue
<pb facs="tcp:1342:10"/>begonne) wyth the ſworde of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and pacient ſuffryng: but plucke vp your hartes lyke valcaunt ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. Beholde with Steuen the Lorde Ieſus ſtandyng at the ryght hande of power,<note place="margin">Act. 7.</note> ready to take your parte, and to helpe you, vpon whome your faith hangeth, and not vpon any worldlye creature. For yf nowe agayne al the diſciples ſhould ſhrynke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and al the brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forſake Paule: yet ſhould<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt and hys worde (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whych ye ſticke, and for the whych Antichriſt dothe perſecute you) be the truthe, and Paule hys faythfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt and Apoſtle. Fynally yf they ſhal (accordyng to theyr moſt cruel cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome) burne you alſo quicke, as that mercyles generacion hathe alredy burned a great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of your fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful paſtours (that gladly gaue theyr liues for theyr flockes) beſides a great number of your innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, doughters, brothers, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and wyues, kynſfolke and frendes, whom they haue in lyke maner conſumed to aſhes, &amp; yet their bloudy appetites is not ſatiſfyed, nor wylbe, ſo long as the long pacience of the Lorde ſhal ſuffre them to haue the
<pb facs="tcp:1342:10"/>ſworde in theyr handes, Yf, I ſaye, they ſhall alſo burne you quicke, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the .iii. chyldren that were throwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in to the fyry fornace,<note place="margin">Dani. 3.</note> becauſe they would not (accordyng to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful commaundement of the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous King Nabuchodonoſor) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with theyr body y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> golden ymage, that he had ſet vp to be worſhipped.</p>
            <p>Remember alſo the holy martyr of Chriſt Policharpus,<note place="margin">Euſe. eccl. li. 4. ca. 15</note> the diſciple of S. Iohn the Euangeliſt: whych beyng threatned by the Iudge that he would burne hym quicke, (as nowe the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes threaten you) made hym aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere and ſaid: Thou threatneſt fyre, that ſhall burne but an houre, &amp; ſone after muſt be quenched: for becauſe thou knoweſt not that fyre of the iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to come, and of the eternal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, that is reſerued for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly. But why taryeſt thou? do what thou wilt. Yf (I ſaye) you ſhalbe by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the aforeſayd wayes, or by any other tormented, aboue all thynges lyft vp your heades, &amp; loke vnto your heade captayne the Lorde Ieſus, the author and fyniſher of your fayth (as S. Paule calleth hym) whych for the ioye that was ſet before him abode the<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:1342:11"/>croſſe, and diſpiſed the ſhame, and is ſet downe on the right hande of the trone of God. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider therfore, howe that he endured ſhuche ſpeakyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt him of ſynners, leſt ye ſhould be wearied &amp; faynt in your myndes.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> The tribulations ar but mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tany, ſhorte, and lyght, but the glory that is prepared for you thorowe Chriſt, is eternal,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 1. Cor. 2. Rom. 8. 1. Pet. 4.</note> immortal, vndefiled, &amp; ſuche as neyther eye hathe ſeen, nor eare heard, nor hath entred in to the harte of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: where of the afflictions of this life are not worthy. Wherfore before al thinges take hede (dearly beloued) that none of you ſuffer as a murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, or as a thefe, or an euill doer, or as a buſibody in other mens maters: but if any of you ſhal after the enſam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of the late bleſſed Martyrs (for which of all the ſhameles Papiſtes, and moſte filthy Sodomites, could or can iuſtely conuince the gloriouſe Martyrs of Chriſt, Ferrar, Hopar, Taylor, Rogers, Sau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, Bradford, Glouer, Cardemaker, or any of them, whome they haue moſte wilfully and maliciouſely murdered, of any nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cryme) if, I ſaye, any of you ſhall after theyr enſample, ſuffer as a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb facs="tcp:1342:11"/>man: let hym not be aſhamed, but let hym glorifye God on thys be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, and committe hys ſoule vnto hym wyth wel doyng, as vnto a fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful creatour. Theſe be in dede, I can not denye, ſtormy and troubleſome dayes, neuertheles yf ye in the holye Gooſt, thorowe the moſte precious death of our alone and omniſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent mediator, the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt Ieſu,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. Hebr. 4.</note> wyl now runne vnto the throne of grace &amp; mercy, and wyl not ceaſe to call vpon our moſt myghty &amp; mercyful father: He wyl vndoutedly, graciouſly heare you, he wyll moſt certaynly delyuer you.<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.</note> For he ſayeth call vpon me in the daye of thy trouble, &amp; I wyl delyuer thee. Here is a moſt playne promyſe of delyueraunce.<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.</note> God is faythful and true in al hys wordes: he neuer fayled any that called faythfully vpon hym. Thys promyſe is ſealed thorowe the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, in whome all goddes promyſes are, yea and Amen.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> Therfore be not weary, be not fainte harted, ſhrynke not.<note place="margin">2. Para. 20.</note> The battail is not yours, but the Lordes. Only ſtande furthe lyke men, and beholde the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des helpe? Saye wyth the moſt noble Ioſaphat,<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> O Lorde ther is no ſtrength
<pb facs="tcp:1342:12"/>in vs to reſyſte theſe furious and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng enemyes of thyne, neither wote we what to do, but only we lyfte vp our eyes vnto thee. Saye wyth the Apoſtles of our Lorde and ſaueour: Now Lorde beholde theyr threatnyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and graunt vnto thy ſeruauntes wyth all confidence and boldnes to ſpeake thy worde.<note place="margin">Dani. 9.</note> Saye wyth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophete Daniel, O Lorde our God thou art ryghteous in al thy workes, we haue iuſtly deſerued all theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that thou haſt brought vpon vs, becauſe we wolde not harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto thy voyce. We haue ſynned o Lord, &amp; done wickedly againſt al thy ryghtfulnes: yet let thy wrathful diſpleaſure be tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned awaye (we beſeche the) from this afflicted realme of Englande, and thy ſorowful congregaciou. O our God enclyne thyne eare and harken, at the leaſt for thyne owne ſake, for thy dear ſonnes ſake, in whoſe name thou haſt promyſed to heare vs. Open thyne eyes, &amp; heholde howe we be deſolate. We caſte not our prayers before thee in our owne ryghteouſnes, but onely in thy great mercyes. O Lorde heare, o forgyue Lorde, o Lorde conſyder, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye not ouer long, moſt myghty Lord
<pb facs="tcp:1342:12"/>and mercyful father we beſeche thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yf we ſhall after thys maner: boldlye and wythout ceaſſyng are, call, ſeke, &amp; knocke at the throne of grace and of mercye, we ſhall certainly fynde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to helpe in the tyme of nede.<note place="margin">Hebr. 4.</note> The vnryghteous Iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neyther feared God, nor cared for man, to be rydde of the importunate ſute &amp; crye of the widowe, herde her requeſt, and auenged her of her enemye. And ſhal not God (ſayeth Chriſt) auenge hys e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte,<note place="margin">Lucc. 18.</note> whych crye daye and nyght vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym, yea though he deferre them? I tel you, ſayeth he, that he wyl aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge them, and that quickely. Marke wel this parable, derely beloued, &amp; it wyll in a maner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pel you, wyl ye, nyl ye, to confeſſe frankely and playnly, that God can not (becauſe he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not denye hymſelfe) but that he muſt nedes hear your prayers, yf ye faynte not, nor ware weary in calling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. This Iudge is not a father, but a tyraunte, and yet neuertheles he herd the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes crie: But God is our father and ſo wold be called of vs,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> and ſhuld he not heare vs? This Iudge is cruell and hathe no compaſſion of other mens calamites. And yet he fulfylled
<pb facs="tcp:1342:13"/>the widowes deſire:<note place="margin">Pſal. 103. Hebre. 4.</note> But God is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally merciful &amp; pitiefull. We haue not ſayeth S. Paule anye prieſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion on our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, but was in al pointes tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted like as we are, but yet w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. And ſhould he contemne our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuall, humble and faythfull ſutes? The Iudge neuer commaunded the wedowe to cum vnto him for healpe, but was rather offeded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her, becauſe ſhe troubled him with her dayly cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng, &amp; neuertheles he herd her: But God hathe commaunded vs to call vpon him.<note place="margin">Pſal. 49 Math. 7. And. 26.</note> Call vpon me (ſayeth he) in the daye of thy trouble: Aſke, ſeke, knocke, ſayeth Chriſt, watche &amp; praye, that ye entre not into temtacion. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng than that he hathe commaunded vs to call vpon hym, wyl he not heare vs, whan we do accordyng to hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement? The Iudge made neuer promyſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wedowe to helpe her, he neuer pmyſed to heare her cauſe, but rather dyd ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes denye eyther to helpe her or heare her: And notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng in concluſion he dyd bothe heare her, and helpe her. But God hathe promyſed to heare vs, and hath not only ſo promyſed, but hath alſo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
<pb facs="tcp:1342:13"/>the ſame with an othe, ſayteng: Verely, verely I ſaye vnto you,<note place="margin">Ioan. 16.</note> what ſo euer ye ſhall aſke the father in my name, he wyl gyue it you: howe is it poſſible nowe, that God ſhould go fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys owne promyſes? To be ſhort,<note place="margin">Luc. 11.</note> the Iuge naturally is euel, and yet do the good vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> widowe in hearyng her cauſe and helpyng her: And wyl not god beyng naturally good, do vs good in hearyng our prayers? Therfore al though God ſemeth nowe to differre vs, &amp; to ſuffer the bloudy and cruel ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, to long to triumphe euer vs: yet let vs not deſpaire, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in prayers, beyng fully perſuaded, that though he ſeme nowe to be farre of, that yet he wyl certeinly come, and delyuer vs. He can not faile nor lye, but wyl come (as the prophete ſayeth) and wyl not tarye.<note place="margin">Aba. 2. Luc. 18. Gen. 15.</note> And I ſaye vnto you (ſayeth Chriſt) that he wil auenge hys electe, and that quyckly. But the iniquitie of the Englyſhe Ammorites is not yet full, neyther theyr cruel ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny yet rype. For ſo fone as theyr wyckednes is ful, and theyr crueltye rype,<note place="margin">Apo. 14.</note> the Lord wyl fende hys reapers to cut them down (as he reuealed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hys ſeruaunt Iohn) and they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:1342:14"/>be caſte into the great wyneſat of the wrath of God: yea they ſhall be theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men into the pyt, that burneth wyth fyre and brimſtone, into that vnque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheable fyre where as ſhalbe wepyng and waylyng,<note place="margin">Apo. 19. Marc. 9.</note> and gnaſhing of tethe. Go to nowe ye tender parnelles, that come in proudely wyth ſtretched out neckes,<note place="margin">Eſa. 3.</note> and wyth vayne wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eyes, trippyng and dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyng ſo nycely with your fete, that can not endure, that a blaſt of the north eaſt wynd in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or that the funne beames in the ſommer, ſhould ones touche the bare of your owne ſtynkyng carcaſes: and yet be ſo mercyles to the poore mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of Chriſt, to honeſt, godly, quiet, and obedient ſubiectes, that neuer of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended you, that would fayne by all meanes pleaſe you (ſo that they might not therby diſpleaſe God) that praye continually to God for your amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (ſo mercyles I ſaye) that you put them into the mouthes of moſte bloudy rauenyng wolfes, &amp; moſt cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe hocherlidogges, to be baited, har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ried, &amp; torne in peces: to be ſpoyled &amp; robbed of landes, houſes, lyuynges, lybertie, goodes, and countreye, to be pinched &amp; pyned in ſtynking priſons,
<pb facs="tcp:1342:14"/>with ſtockes, fetters, chaines, rackes, colde, famine and other rigorous tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: to be ſtrangled with halters, to ſpille theyr innocent bloude wyth ſwordes &amp; axes, to burne them quicke to aſhes, Go to I ſaye you tender par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelles, that be nowe ſo tender &amp; dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ouer your owne vyle fleſhe,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5. and. 1. 1. Cor. 6.</note> and ſo mercyles to the fleſhe, bloud, bones, bodies, and membres of Chriſt, &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples of the holy Gooſt: tell me what wyll ye do in the tyme of the viſitaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deſtruccion,<note place="margin">Eſa. 10. Pro. 1.</note> that ſhal come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you ſodaynly, lyke a ſtorme &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peſt? To whom wyl ye ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne for helpe? or to whome wyll ye gyue your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that he maye kepe it? that ye co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me not among the priſoners, or lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the deade?<note place="margin">Eſa. 66. Mar. 9.</note> Tel me (I praye you) howe well you ſhalbe able to endure that vnquencheable fyre, wherin for your manyfolde, blodye tyrannies, &amp; murtheryng of Goddes people, you ſhall moſt certaynly burne worlde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wepyng, wayling, &amp; gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhinh of tethe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which are prepared for the deuil &amp; hys au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels. Neither ſhall your Romiſhe pardons, nor your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domitical maſſemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers with al theyr tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pery, be able to plucke you out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyry lake:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1342:15"/>
            <p> When as ye ſhall ſe the ryghteous ſtande in great ſtedfaſtnes agaynſt you,<note place="margin">Sap. 5.</note> that haue dealt ſo extremely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaye theyr labours, when you beyng vexed wyth an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible feare, and wonderyng at the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne health, glorious kyngdome, &amp; beautiful crowne, whych the ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhal receyue at the Lordes hande, and gronyng for very diſtreſſe &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guyſhe of mynde, ſhall ſaye wythin your ſelues. Theſe are they whome we ſometyme had in deriſion, and ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We fooles thought their life very madnes, &amp; theyr ende to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out honour: but lo howe they are counted among the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, and theyr porcion is among the ſayntes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we haue erred from the waye of trueth, the lyght of ryghteouſnes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the not ſhyned vnto vs, and the ſunne of vnderſtandyng roſe not vpon vs. We haue wearyed our ſelues in the waye of wyckednes, and deſtruccion. Tedious wayes haue we gone, but the waye of the Lorde we haue not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen. What good hath our pryde done vnto vs? or what profyte hathe the pompe of ryches brought vs? al thoſe thynges are paſſed awaye lyke a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe.
<pb facs="tcp:1342:15"/>&amp;c. O ye proude and bloudy Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſtes, ſuche miſerable wordes ſhal ye ſpeake beyng in hell, and burnyng in fyre vnquencheable wyth the deuell &amp; hys aungels, whoſe kyngdome you haue promoted, maynteyned, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. Wherfore (deare brethren) be not greued at theyr moſte vayne pom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pous,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37. And. 73.</note> and ſhorte pryde, and glorious welthe, thorowe the whyche they are become ſo maliciouſly wood, to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe dayly ſuche furious &amp; monſtrous madneſſe and tyrannye, agaynſt the Lorde Chriſt, hys Goſpell, &amp; hys pure membres: but conſydre ye the moſt horrible endes of Pharao,<note place="margin">Exod. 14. 1. Reg. 31. 2. Mac. 9. Act. 2. Euſe. eccl. Li. 9. ca. 9 Theod. li. 4. cap. 25.</note> Saul, Anti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ochus, Herode, Maxencius, Iulianus the apoſtata, and ſuche other tyraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whoſe endes the tyrauntes of the Popiſhe Sodomites and princes of Gomorra wyl ſhortly folowe: And ſo thou ſhalt haue iuſte cauſe rather to lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the moſt myſerable ſtate, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in they are now holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> captiue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, than to folowe theyr curſed &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elenterpryſes. The Lorde (ſayeth Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid) hath ſet them in a ſlippery place,<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> that he maye caſte them downe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges, and deſtroye them. O howe ſodenly do they conſume, peryſhe, and
<pb facs="tcp:1342:16"/>come to a fearfull ende? yea euen as a dreame wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one awaketh. So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou theyr ymage to vaniſhe out of the cytie. Thys had Dauid founde true by erperience, therfore in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> I my ſelfe (ſayeth he) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſene the vngodly in great power, &amp; floryſhe lyke a grene Baye tree: but I went by, lo he was gone, I ſought him, but he coulde no where be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Kepe ye therfore innocency, and take hede vnto the thyng that is ryght. Sit ſtil, be quyet, and pacient, embrace &amp; kyſſe the Lordes rodde:<note place="margin">Eſa. 30.</note> For in quyet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and in hope (ſayeth the Lorde) ſhall your ſtrength lye. Call vpon God wythout ceaſſyng, and in your prayers be myndfull of the afflicted, oppreſſed &amp; ſcatered churche of Chriſt, whych is nowe once agayne almoſt rooted vp by the wylde Bore of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 80.</note> and other of that ſwyniſhe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion, that God for hys mercy ſake maye yet agayne (yf it be hys bleſſed wyll) buylde vp the walles of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50. and. 124.</note> and turne aways the captiuitie of our Syon.</p>
            <p>¶ The God of all grace,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> whych hathe called you vnto hys eternall glory by
<pb facs="tcp:1342:16"/>Chriſt Ieſu, ſhal hys owne ſelfe (after ye haue ſuffred a lytle affliccion) make you parfyte, ſetle, ſtrengtht, and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſhe you. To hym be glorye and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion for euer, and whyle the world endure. Amen. The peace of God, the ſtrength and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of the holy Gooſt,<note place="margin">Ephi. 6.</note> be wyth you al that loue the Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. AMEN.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Apoca. 22.</bibl>
               <q>Veni Domme Ieſu cito.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Anno. 1555.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
